A Guide to the Baughman Family Papers, 1837-1968, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Baughman Family Papers, 1837-1968, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Baughman, Charles C. (Charles Christian), 1842-1908; Baughman, George, Jr., b. abt. 1837; Baughman, George, Sr., 1809-1870; Baughman, Greer H. (Greer Harry), 1840-1907; Baughman, Mary Amelia (Minnie), 1847-1917; Baughman, Mary Jane Greer, 1811-1898
Ms2018-031
1.9 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
The Baughman Family Papers contain correspondence between members of the Baughman family of Richmond, Virginia, as well as with friends, written from 1837 to 1957 (bulk, 1837-1907). The second part of the collection is family papers from about 1859 to the 1940s. This includes military documents, estate papers, legal documents, Confederate society papers, poetry, and photographs.
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Baughman Family Papers were purchased by Special Collections in July 2018.
Biographical Note: Charles C. Baughman
Charles Christian Baughman was born to George and Mary Jane (Greer) Baughman about 1842, in Maryland. The family relocated to Salem, Virginia, in 1847, and later to Richmond, in 1856. Charles enlisted with Company F, 21st Regiment, Virginia Infantry (along with two of his brothers), in April of 1861. He mustered out March 1862, then transferred to the Copmany A, Richmond Otey Battery, Light Artillery. Following the Civil War, he and his brothers took over their father's stationary business, forming Baughman Bros. in Richmond. Charles married Willette Harrison Stevens (1852-1893) and they had one son, Greer. In 1900, he was living with his brother, Greer, and his sister, Mary Amelia (Minnie). He died in March 1908.
Biographical Note: Emilius A. Baughman
Emilius Allen Baughman was born to George and Mary Jane (Greer) Baughman in 1844 in Maryland. The family relocated to Salem, Virginia, in 1847, and later to Richmond, in 1856. At the age of 18, in 1863, he followed his father and older brothers, and enlisted in the Confederate army with 38th Battalion, Virginia Light Artillery (Read's). His brother Greer was already a member of the unit. Following the Civil War, he and his brothers took over their father's stationary business, forming Baughman Bros. in Richmond. In 1873, Emilius married Mary Barney in Richmond, and the couple had 8 children. Emilius died in 1915 and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Note: George Baughman, Jr.
George Baughman, Jr. was born to George and Mary Jane (Greer) Baughman about 1837, in Maryland. The family relocated to Salem, Virginia, in 1847, and later to Richmond, in 1856. enlisted with Company F, 21st Regiment, Virginia Infantry (along with two of his brothers), in April of 1861. There are no records of George following the war, so it is unclear when he died. However, there is a George Baughman buried with the family in Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia, who died in 1882.
Biographical Note: George Baughman, Sr.
George Baughman was both to John and Barbara Baughman at Yellow Breeches Creek, in the Susquehanna Valley of Pennsylvania, August 15, 1809. By the mid-1830s, he had relocated to Baltimore, Maryland. In September 1835, he married Mary Jane Greer (1811-1898). The couple had six children, five of whom lived to adulthood: George, Jr., Greer, Charles, Emilius, and Mary Amelia (Minnie). In 1847, Baughman moved his family to Salem, Virginia, and in 1856, to Richmond, Virginia. In Richmond, he was a newspaper man and founded a stationary business that was operated by his sons following the Civil War. Baughman served in the Confederate Ambulance Corps (1st Regiment, Virginia State Reserves (2nd Class Militia) during the Civil War. His four sons also served. Baughman returned to Richmond and lived there until his death in 1870. He is buried in Hollywood Cemeterry, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Note: Greer H. Baughman
Greer H. Baughman was born to George and Mary Jane (Greer) Baughman about 1840, in Maryland. The family relocated to Salem, Virginia, in 1847, and later to Richmond, in 1856. Greer enlisted with the 21st Regiment, Virginia Infantry (along with two of his brothers), in April of 1861. In July 1861, he transferred to the Hampden Artilley, with which his youngest brother would later enlist. Greer was wounded in June 1864 and spent over a month in the Confederate hospital at Chimborazo, before returning to his regiment for the remainder of the war. Greer married Francis H. (Willie) Richardson (b. 1845, d.before 1900) on August 15, 1866. They had one daughter, May (1868-1952). Following the Civil War, he and his brothers took over their father's stationary business, forming Baughman Bros. in Richmond. Greer died in 1907 and is buried in the Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Note: Mary Amelia (Minnie) Baughman
Mary Amelia (Minnie) Baughman was born in March 1847 to George and Mary Jane Greer Baughman in Maryland. The family relocated to Salem, Virginia, in 1847, and later to Richmond, in 1856. Minnie appears to have never married. In 1900, she was living with her two widowed brothers, Charles and Greer. Minnie died in 1917 and is buried in the Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Note: Mary Jane Greer Baughman
Mary Jane Greer Baughman was born in New Orleans, Louisiana, on August 25, 1811. Her family moved to Baltimore, Maryland, prior to 1825. In September 1835, she married George Baughman (1809-1870) and the couple had 6 children: George, Jr., Greer, Charles, Emilius, Mary Amelia (Minnie), and Frank (who died as a child). She died on April 25, 1898, and is buried in Hollywood Cemeterry, Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Contents
The Baughman Family Papers contain correspondence between members of the Baughman family of Richmond, Virginia, as well as with friends, written from 1837 to 1957 (bulk, 1837-1907). This includes extensive letters written between family members during the Civil War. George Baughman, Sr., and his four sons all served with the Confederacy. In addition to letters between the family, there are additional letters from the extended Baughman and Greer families, business correspondence (George Baughman ran a stationary business before and after the Civil War, later taken over by his sons), and ephemeral correspondence materials (calling cards, postcards, invitations, greeting cards, and telegrams). The second part of the collection is family papers from about 1859 to the 1940s. This includes military documents, estate papers, legal documents, Confederate society papers, poetry, and photographs.
Arrangement
The Baughman Family Papers consist of two series. Series I: Correspondence, 1837-1957, n.d. (bulk, 1837-1907) contains two subseries. Subseries A: Letters, includes correspondence from before, during, and after the Civil War. In addition, there are letters from the extended Baughman and Greer families, business associates of George Baughman, Sr., and his sons, and collections of calling and greeting cards, invitations, postcards, and telegrams. This subseries is organized chronologically within each major correspondent. Subseries B: Other Correspondence Items contains calling cards, envelopes not attached to other letters, greeting cards, invitations, postcards, and telegrams sent to the family between the mid-19th and early 20th centuries. This subseries is organized by format.
Series II: Family Papers consists of military papers of John L. Boatwright 1942-1943, family photographs, copies of poetry and Confederate songs, estate papers many pertaining to Greer Baughman from 1900-1907, legal documents from 1868-1921, business papers primarily written by Greer Baughman, and miscellaneous papers from Confederate Veterans' Societies in Richmond, Virginia. This series is organized by type of material. Folders in the series are in alphabetical by folder title (type of material).
Related Materials
Greer and Emilius Baughman Civil War Letters to Mary Jane Baughman, 1862-1863 (Ms2018-037). Finding aid available online.
Greer and Emilius Baughman Civil War Letters, 1862-1865 (Ms2018-036). Finding aid available online.
Minnie A. Baughman Commonplace Book, 1864-1865 (Ms2018-038). Finding aid available online.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Petersburg (Va.) -- History -- Siege, 1864-1865
Geographical Names:
Richmond, Virginia; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Artillery. 13th Battalion; Baltimore (Md.)--1860-1910
Occupations:
Businesspeople
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1837-1957, n.d. (bulk, 1837-1907)
  - Subseries A: Letters
    - Charles C. Baughman Correspondence, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Charles C. Baughman Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Charles C. Baughman Correspondence, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - George Baughman, Jr., Correspondence, 1861-1865 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Greer H. Baughman Correspondence, 1861-1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Greer H. Baughman Correspondence, 1864-1865 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Greer H. Baughman Correspondence, 1865-1866 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Greer H. Baughman Correspondence, 1871-1883 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Greer H. Baughman Correspondence, 1899-1904 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Greer H. Baughman Correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Greer H. Baughman Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Minnie A. Baughman Correspondence, 1861-1864 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Minnie A. Baughman Correspondence, 1896-1903 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Minnie A. Baughman Correspondence, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Minnie A. Baughman Correspondence, 1865-1867 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Minnie A. Baughman Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Minnie A. Baughman Correspondence, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Civil War Correspondence to the Baughman Family, 1861-1864 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Baughman/Greer Family Correspondence, 1837-1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Baughman Family Correspondence, 1865-1869 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Baughman Family Correspondence, 1871-1886 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Baughman Family Correspondence, 1890-1895 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Anne B. Layne Correspondence, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Baughman Family Correspondence, 1901-1907 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1912-1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Baughman Family Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Subseries B: Other Correspondence Items
    - Calling Cards, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Envelopes (3 folders), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30-32)
    - Greeting Cards, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Invitations, 1878-1895 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Postcards and Telegrams, 1883-1907 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Series II: Family Papers, 1859-1943, n.d.
  - Account Books, 1901-1910 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Address Book, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Confederate Furlough Approval, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Confederate Societies, Richmond, Virginia (2 folders), 1893-1915 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
  - Estate Papers (2 folders), 1900-1907 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - John L. Boatwright Coast Guard Papers, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Legal and Insurance Documents, 1868-1921 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Newspaper Clippings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Printed Ephemera, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Poetry, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Pubilcations, 1859, 1908, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Publications, 1916-1918, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Receipts (2 folders), 1891-1907 (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - Tickets and Invitations, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)